so I guess I first came across Jordan
Peterson about nine or ten months ago
something like that and what actually
first made me sit up and take notice of
him was he was in an interview who's
discussing materialist science and some
of his issues with that and he was
saying that the hard problem of
materials that the material science is
consciousness and that as far as he was
concerned consciousness was the means by
which we turned or turn I should say the
chaos of potential that constantly
surrounds us into meaningful manageable
order and that really perked up my ears
because as someone who's done quite a
lot of psychedelics that sense of
somehow assembling our reality you know
drawing it into focus from from around
us really dived with my own experience
and so I shortly after that became aware
of the interview that he did with Kathy
Newman which went viral and I really
started to pay attention to him because
you know he was someone who for really
the first time I can think about in
recent times was actually trying to
shine a light on the true nature on the
actualities of a situation and so
although this video is actually
primarily about a couple of issues that
I have with a couple of fundamental
precepts I want to spend the first part
of it establishing my credentials as it
were as someone who is not going to try
and misrepresent him because he has been
horribly willfully shamelessly
misrepresented at times in the media and
so yet to establish my credibility as
someone who a basically really likes
what he has to say
and be that I and you know that I get it
I'm not I'm not I'm not trying to not
try to twist his ideas in any way so
yeah I mean primarily I'm grateful for
the fact that he has raised the level of
complexity and the level of truthfulness
that is required in debate at least in
some circles and some of his ideas are
really beautiful he gave a couple of
very impassioned speeches that I saw
about free speech and political
correctness and it ties together nicely
with one of the stories he retails in
his Bible lectures so you know he gave
the speech about free speech where he
said the free speech is not just about
the ability to speak freely and to
challenge the powerful although of
course it is also those things but more
fundamentally that is the way that we
assemble meaningful order from chaos and
so if you confront the world
forthrightly
with forthright action and truthful
speech then the order you will create
from the world is good and this is this
is what in his opinion the story of
Genesis is all about that God created
the world or the Word of God created the
world in the world was good and then and
so if you do as God did as it were and
then that's not how he means that this
is it's not the way he retells the Bible
stories is not as revealed truth Word of
God kind of thing it's about wisdom
assembled over long periods of time as
to how best to go about living a
meaningful fulfilling life on this earth
and so free speech is not just about as
I said speaking freely and challenging
the powerful but is the means by which
we assemble our reality and if you
assemble order from chaos by using
anything less than forthright action and
truthful speech then the order that you
will assemble will be less than good and
potentially very ugly so I think this is
a really lovely idea and you know there
are a few that have stuck with me
another one is his prime one of his
other primary missions has been to
empower people at the individual level
by explaining that the kind of meaning
and fulfillment that you find in life
that not only gives you joy in your good
times but sustains you through your bad
times is to be found in the adoption of
personal responsibility and so you know
not complaining and whining but actually
doing your best to fix the circumstances
of your life and taking responsibility
for it when it goes wrong and I think
that he's absolutely right that the
correct level of analysis with which to
fix the problems of society or the
individual level but later on I do kind
of wish to take issue with
with that in part and that if you do not
do that if you do not bring the best of
yourself into this world if you do not
manifest the talents that that are that
are latent within you then what
manifests in the world instead is
potentially something ugly and
unpleasant and even evil and I think
this is a really lovely idea another one
not related in any way with another one
that really stuck with me was was the
concept that constraint can create
possibility or does create possibility
uses as these as an example the game of
chess so in the game of chess you have
64 squares 32 of them white photos and
black you got 32 pieces 16 white 16
black but without the rules of the game
you've you've got nothing you just
whatever you just throw pieces around it
has no meaning only when you impose the
constraints of this piece must move in
this way one player must play after the
other this is the objective which you
are trying to reach only then do the
strategies and the ways of thinking and
so on and become possible and so
constraint creates meaning and
possibility and I love that idea in a
like manner when you're learning a
musical instrument you don't have
absolute freedom you know here's a
guitar go at it kind of thing or at
least unless you're a complete genius
and natural genius at it but you know
for most people the beginning process is
a giving up of your personal freedom in
order to learn the rules or if you know
how to pick the notes how to construct
the chords how to read the music etc etc
only when you have learned those rules
any of them when you've learned that
structured to a high level of
proficiency can you then begin to
express yourself you know your inner
self through your music and so the idea
of you know having absolute freedom to
do anything at any time yeah this is
it's kind of meaningless you know the
idea of God as an omnipotent omniscient
being what would an omnipotent
omniscient being relax is limitation
either this is this is this is a
massively important
I do to my own thinking and I'm
extremely grateful to him for it
extremely grateful to him for presenting
it to me but as I said before above all
I really like the fact that he talks
about the actualities of a situation in
that Kathy Newman interview for example
the main theme of that interview was the
gender pay gap between men and women in
the UK and he was attempting any way to
explained that this is not just about
you're a woman he's a man therefore
we're going to pay you less that
actually the difference the apparent
difference in pay between men and women
was was was it was a multi variable
thing that was caused by many many many
things personality traits choices that
men women tend to make and that you know
although if you look at any given man
any random man in any random woman
there's not likely to be a huge amount
of difference in personality or choices
when you go out to the extremes the most
aggressive people are all men which is
one of the prison population is
primarily male and the most agreeable
people are all women which is one of the
reasons why they don't challenge for
promotion and higher pay awards and so
on as aggressively as men do so you know
the the reality of the situation is
almost always far more complex and less
about compassion and virtue signaling
them them then it may first appear to be
one of the things I thought he was very
brave about was his was a couple of
comments he made about climate change I
think it was at the Cambridge Union he
was asked by a very pompous sounding
student a question about climate change
and would this be the issue that would
finally unite mankind and he says
absolutely not no it's almost impossible
to separate the science from the
politics we don't really know what to do
about it and that any action that we
take is the effectiveness is almost
impossible to measure because the error
bars get wider than the effect of the
action quite quickly and so you know for
all of these reasons he doesn't think
we're going to do anything about it and
and this is an incredibly brave start he
also circulated on his Twitter account a
University of Prager University
video of which
questioning some of the prevailing
narratives about climate change and it
was funny how a lot of even his own
support has turned on him I'm part of a
discussion group which is primarily
populated by jordan peterson fans and
even there there were quite a few of
them saying oh well if that's his stance
on climate change i'm going to stop
listening to him which is you know for
me and I think for Jordan Peters and so
this is one of the prevailing sicknesses
of our society is that you know just
because somebody says or does one thing
that you know you find abhorrent does
not mean that you automatically dismiss
every single thing that they have said
or done you know it's a real it's a real
sickness his other lecture series on
YouTube is called maps of meaning and
that is it's a kind of about exactly
that the dangers of excessive control of
dialogue in the population he primarily
looking at the idea of totalitarianism
and attempting to answer the question if
I was living in a state where the
totalitarian narrative was picking up
pace what kind of work would I need to
do to myself in order to be the sort of
person who would not go along with that
narrative who would resist who would who
who would try and affect you know an
alternate narrative and it amounts to no
less than a grand exploration of both
individual and collective psychology
through a variety of lenses which he
brings together with the incredible
skill and and and articulation and draws
on philosophy draws on psychology draws
on biblical narratives draws on social
narratives draws on historical example
draws on the novels of a couple of
people you know there's a really broad
landscape of sources on which he draws
as it's a profoundly challenging piece
of work which I highly recommend you
spend the time watching even though you
know it's a 40 or 50 hour commitment but
you know do it in bits it's well worth
the effort his educational and personal
development programs as well I mean
listen the guy's making a lot of money
out of the
there's no question about it however he
is I remain convinced that his heart is
absolutely in the right place but as I
said the start I do wish to question a
couple of his underlying assumptions and
that's what I'm going to do in the
second part of the video there are three
areas on a focus on I'll do them one at
a time with a little banner at the start
of each one to tell you what it's about
okay so the first one I want to look at
is his talk about hierarchies it's gonna
take me a while to unpack this because I
first want to summarize his own line of
thinking and then talk about what my
issue is with it so the first chapter of
his book is stand up straightening the
shoulders back and it's a talk about
exactly that hierarchy and he starts
with lobsters and talks about how you
know the biggest strongest lobster gets
the best catch and access to the hottest
women and all that kind of thing and
that the brain pathway in chemistry
responsible for a lobsters recognition
of its position in the hierarchy is the
same as we have in our own in our own
brains in our own chemistry he then goes
on to look at the evolving complexities
of hierarchies and you know goes from
lobsters to wolves and fools to
chimpanzees and talks about how it's not
just the biggest strongest wolf or the
biggest strongest chimpanzee that is
leader of the pack because the Sociology
is more complex and so you know with
chimpanzees in particular the biggest
strongest chimp if he's just a ugly
vicious tyrant world two or three other
chimps will get together and bring him
down and so you know just being the
biggest and the strongest is not enough
yeah you've got to be big and strong but
you also have to be able to negotiate
relationships within the group in order
to maintain your position and he then
goes on to talk about human hierarchies
and that human hierarchies are a whole
new evolution of the concept because
within human society we can create new
hierarchies and so you have hierarchies
of builders you have hierarchies of
musicians you have hierarchies of
accountants and so on and so on and so
on so you have lots and lots of
different hierarchies and in a healthy
society there are a sufficient variety
of hierarchies that everybody can find a
position of some significance in some
hierarchy somewhere or other and and
therefore find some meaning and some
purpose in their lives
he then talks about how all hierarchy
these are susceptible to or tilt towards
I think is the phrase that he uses
corruption and tyranny and that you can
recognize corruption attorney taking
place in a hierarchy when people
exercise power and influence in order to
ascend the hierarchy rather than merit
that a healthy hierarchy people ascend
the hierarchy because they're good at
doing that thing you know so it's merit
it's competence is the word that he uses
which allows a healthy hierarchy to be
ascended and with all of that I broadly
agree I don't take issue with any of
that
I think I thought I think it's a I think
it's a very well laid out schema however
where I do take issue with him is where
he starts to talk about how Western
society is broadly healthy hierarchies
because they are based on competence and
he gives the example of you know how you
don't have bands of tyrannical plumbers
going up and down the street demanding
that you use their services that
plumbers are selected on the basis of
their ability to do the job when you
want it to a sufficiently high level of
competence and again I agree with all of
that where I think he I don't know if he
willfully omits it or simply doesn't
fully appreciate it or maybe simply
disagrees with with what I'm about to
say but the hierarchies in which all
other hierarchies are embedded are those
where the true power resides so we're
talking about finance we're talking
about government and politics we're
talking about corporate influence and
all other hierarchies are embedded
within that particularly the money
hierarchy I mean you you can't really
get anything done in this world without
the use of money in some way or another
and so you know those that control the
the super hierarchies if you like in
which all of the others are embedded are
at a significant advantage and I think
he profoundly underestimates the degree
to which our super hierarchies are
indeed
corrupt and I give us examples the
revolving door that exists between high
levels of government and Finance I mean
one example that springs to mind is hank
paulson who you know previously senior
executive at goldman sachs becomes
treasury secretary at the time of the
crash allows lehman brothers to collapse
while at the same time it's you know
insisting that AIG get bailed out
because AIG held huge contracts for
Goldman Sachs which Goldman Sachs were
really I think I could be wrong about
this I think the number was seven
billion dollars of payouts AIG would do
to make to Goldman Sachs in insurance
payouts and have they gone under they
wouldn't have been able to do that look
at the Iraq war look at the bonus
painless made of bankers after the
financial crash you know they look at
the amount of lobbying that goes on look
at the Buckley and Valeo and Citizens
United decisions which respectively
defined corporations as people and
defined money as speech and so
corporations can now spend as much money
as they want on buy political influence
you know these these hierarchies are
deeply deeply corrupted and I have a
little bit of an issue with his blase
sweeping off as Western society is
broadly functional yeah there's little
bits of corruption here and there but
it's broadly functional I disagree with
that profoundly I think that our super
hierarchies as I refer to them early on
the the real controlling hierarchies are
controlled by a very few people for
their own ends I don't think there can
be any doubt of that in the light of all
the stuff that we've seen since the
advent of the internet and so much Alden
Peterson talks about the correct level
of analysis for getting at the root
causes of the problems of society is the
individual I I broadly agree with that
however when there are systemic barriers
to that occurring then those systemic
barriers needs to be examined very
carefully and I think there's a big gap
in the fairness of his expectation where
when you look at the way that
individuals and nations are hamstrung by
some deeply flawed systems that we have
I mean just just one for example our
system of money because 97% of money is
created as debt and debt carries
interest you have this constant constant
ever-increasing shortfall in the money
supply with a greater and greater demand
on the existing supply of money to be
paid out an interest payment so less and
less to actually go around and do
commerce you know that it necessarily
impoverishes increasing that increasing
numbers of people and this is what we
see going on around us and it's all very
well saying that you know lifted this
many people out of starvation this many
children are getting this much more to
eat in blah blah blah but you know this
is not the this the idea that things are
broadly getting better this is not most
people's experience certainly not in the
working and middle classes of the
developed world one final thought on
this is Jordan Peterson's use of the
Pareto distribution to justify is too
strong but to explain as somewhat
inevitable very large disparities of
wealth in society and again I don't deny
the existence of the freeter
distribution my issue with this line of
thinking is that whatever inequality in
resource distribution might naturally
manifest themselves we have chosen
systems which exacerbate that you know
we have we have a system of money we're
essentially obviously more complex in
this but essentially which people earn
money support because rich people have a
surplus of money so they've entered the
poor people earlier interesting pay it
back with interest and so rich people
accumulate more money and poor people
get poorer because thing is having to
pay money to rich people and yeah sure a
few a few poor people strike it rich and
become rich people but you know for the
most part it's a it's a it's a game
where money is inevitably drawn away
from most people towards a very very few
people and you know I he talks about
Maslow's hierarchy as being flawed
because
if you accept the reality of Maslow's
hierarchy then rich people must
necessarily be more moral than poor
people because they've had more of their
needs met and therefore they've ascended
higher up the hierarchy and we all know
from our own daily experience that rich
people are no more moral than poor
people but the fact of the matter is
it's very much easier to think about you
know working on yourself as an
individual if your base needs are met
and while very very large numbers of
people are basically living
hand-to-mouth struggling to survive day
to day they don't have time to think
about them so they don't have time to
think about society at large they don't
have time to educate themselves or
broaden their minds you know what I mean
they're there they're busy raising kids
on no money so I I think he does a
disservice to reality if you like by by
failing to acknowledge fully the extent
to which people are disempowered by
systemic barriers anyway let's move on
to the next one
this is my this this issue's probably a
slightly a little bit more nebulous it's
linked to his railing against political
correctness and the dangers of political
correctness than the impact that it can
have on freedom of speech because
freedom of speech is not about being
free to say things that people agree
with but being free to say things that
people don't agree with and that is
likely to upset or offend them and the
ability to do that is necessary in order
to have difficult conversations about
difficult complex topics you have to run
the risk of offending people in order
for thinking to take place he makes the
point that thinking is rarely done on
one's own very very few people have the
capacity to actually think to doubt to
question to really seek to undermine the
presuppositions on which the argument is
based which is necessary for actual you
know actual progress actual thinking
actual new ideas to take place and so
this leads onto his dialogue about the
proper roles of the left and right in
political discussion that the right
fights for the validity of hierarchies
hierarchies are necessary in order for a
group to undertake activities
hierarchies are going to be created and
that they're necessary and that they are
good if you like the role of the left is
to highlight the fact that hierarchies
dispossessed lots and lots of people at
the bottom and to be fair to mr.
Peterson he does acknowledge the fact
that our hierarchies do dis possess very
large numbers of the people at the
bottom and and dispossessed with zero
and equally he acknowledges that getting
from zero to something is very very much
harder than getting from something to
more as I said before I think he under
plays the extent to which our systems
are responsible for that and kind of
over plays the impersonal forces like
the frito distribution but anyway well
I've already talked about that what I
want to talk about here is the left hat
the left versus right thing as it
relates to the road to totalitarianism
and so
I've kind of laid the groundwork and so
those are the proper roles are the left
and right and that we know the right has
gone too far when they start talking
about racial purity or superiority or
whatever but we don't really yet have an
understanding of where the left has gone
too far in that despite his decades of
research and writing on the subject he
doesn't think that he fully understands
what the warning signals are when we're
going down the left-hand road to
totalitarianism so I kind of take issue
with the whole meta suppositions on
which this this discussion is based
because as far as I'm concerned and
listen I'm nowhere near as well read or
as well educated on the topic as he is
and I'm quite willing to accept the
possibility that I'm missing something
here however as far as I can see
totalitarianism is totalitarianism it
isn't it is an attempt by the state to
absolutely control the doings of its
people right down to you know right down
to the last detail and in order to
accomplish that needs to have very
strong structures and institutions in
place in order to surveil and coerce its
population into doing things it might
not otherwise wish to do that's that
that's what I see totalitarian and now
whether you go down the left or the
right doesn't seem to me to make any
difference and for someone who is so
meticulous about exploring and seeking
truth uncovering layers and layers of
you know removing veils and veils in
order to get to the truth I find it
extraordinary that his answer to the
question of when is the right content
fire is a simplistic as racial hatred
whatever superiority whatever it may be
and you know it seems to me that the
wrote of totalitarianism is when the
state starts to exert excessive control
over the thoughts and actions of its
people and it seems to me that whether
that goes
via the pervert you know via fascism or
via communism is absolutely irrelevant
both of these things are giant state
structures controlling its people
through a combination of brainwashing
and coercion and you know I really
really don't understand what the
distinction is that he's trying to draw
and I can understand to a certain extent
even though it doesn't jibe with
anything that he actually says but given
the vehement aunty left
start that he takes the anti extreme
left stance that he takes and kind of
dismisses as tap well that's all right
they're not talking about racial stuff
therefore they're not too far off the
map that seems to me to be a little bit
of a distortion not to mention a gross
oversimplification state control over
its people is manifest in its desire to
control the narrative which as far as I
can see through mainstream media the
state does a very good job of
controlling the narrative and telling us
what we ought to be thinking and making
sure it knows what its citizenry is up
to and you know given revelations from
Snowden and others as to the extent to
which we are under constant surveillance
is particularly our web presence you
know our social media presence our
searches search histories etc etc and
the degree to which we are surveilled
and profiled primarily for marketing
purposes and nothing more sinister than
that but nevertheless the apparatus
exists for the state to control and I
don't understand why he's not more
worried about these things I really I
really don't understand why he doesn't
see us as being further down the road
towards totalitarianism than we are and
this whole left-right thing seems to me
to be a distraction from a permanent on
unelected state apparatus which is
taking us further and further down the
road towards totalitarianism and for
someone who is as well-informed
well-read and well versed in the subject
as jordan peterson is i find his
oversimplification of this kind of stuff
to be
a bit suspects I also think is what's
the word extremely offhand dismissal of
anything leftist or Marxist is is also
somewhat simplistic I mean socialism at
its core is about society rights in the
word social is in its in the word it's
about creating a functional dynamic
healthy vigorous society and having skin
in the game is essential to that you
know the the whole labor for money
contract is an aberration to most clever
classical economists you know if you
don't have skin in the game you don't
care about what you're doing and you are
on the road towards eventual
impoverishment because the assets the
real value remains in the hands of the
owners is not distributed among
everybody else anyway I'm going slightly
off-topic here my real issue is with the
left-right distinction when it comes to
totalitarianism as far along so
totalitarianism mister territorialism
and and and what color it may have
started out as is irrelevant that whole
color thing is a distraction Trump is a
distraction brexit is a distraction now
five-year Lee elections are a
distraction from the reality of what's
going on that we are under tighter and
tighter and tighter control by this
apparatus which is not the state as we
understand it not the elected
representatives of the state as we
understand it of course another feature
of totalitarianism is stifling dissent
censorship being a primary tool of that
and Jordan Peterson has himself recently
closed down his patreon account and is
going to be transferring to his own
website as are other people that I know
because of the censoring or the sorry I
should say the D platforming of Carl
Benjamin also known as Sagwa Novak had
four things that he said not even on
patreon not even on his own channel
while being interviewed for somebody
else on other platform so you know
censorship is picking up pace and
running
rampant and once again I don't
understand why mr. Peterson isn't more
concerned about how far down the road we
are towards totalitarianism
third and final points of disagreement
or major point of disagreement is to do
with religion and Christianity and let
me start by reiterating I think what
he's done with the Bible stories is
remarkable I've learned a huge amount
from what I've seen of those lectures I
haven't watched all of I've watched
about half of them but I've learned a
huge amount from what I've seen from
those lectures and once again the way he
draws in other sources to create this
broad perspective from which to view
them has been for me anyway entirely
original and and a wonderful thing
however specifically with Christianity
and this is the religion with which he
most clearly identifies himself
obviously I don't think that's I don't
think that's open to dispute has at its
core something which i think is
profoundly damaging and and I would like
to explore a little bit here so I'm
pretty sure it's in a story of Noah that
God undertakes to man never to do the
whole flood thing ever again and gives
him dominion over the earth and over the
animals and so um you know this story
along with I suspect many others I'm no
biblical scholar I don't I don't know
the Bible well reinforces something
which to me is at the very very very
core of Christianity which is an idea of
separation between God man and nature
it's it's like a triumvirate of three
separate things that God created nature
God created man got inserted man into
nature and God gave man dominion over
nature and these ideas which I think run
deep deep deep in the psyche of the
Western mind are responsible in my
opinion for a huge amount of the
external and internal destruction guy
at the moment to give you an idea of
what I'm talking about the or a better
idea sure I should say what I'm talking
about in the Eastern philosophies in
Buddhism for example God or the Buddha
or whatever is is in all things right I
mean all things both animate and
inanimate as
we would call them contain within them
the Buddha and so what you do to the
world around you you also do to yourself
it's one continuous interconnected
inseparable thing and you know every
single thing is a manifestation of God
is a manifestation of the Buddha and as
I said that which you do to your world
you do in a very very real way to
yourself because you are the world and
the world is you and to me this
connectedness with the world around you
with nature with everybody else seeing
all things as God manifest in physical
form or whatever I I think this is
absent from Christianity and is for me
the biggest reason not to be of that I
mean I listen the teachings of Jesus
Christ the brotherhood of man and
forgiveness and tolerance and
understanding and love and all of that
absolutely all on board with that he was
by no means the first person to preach
that kind of thing but the the the the
mythology that underlies it and that
separation of God from man from nature
and again I'm quite willing to accept
that there is a deficiency in my own
understanding of Christianity like I
said I am no scholar but that that does
seem to me to be and I'm not the only
one to think this as um Joseph
Oh God his name escapes me
begins of the sea I can't think of his
name it'll come to me anyway
talks about this also about about this
failing in Christianity that it fails to
appreciate the divine in all things you
know that all things have a soul all
beings have a soul is not unique to man
and this sense of superiority that man
has and that he has the right to impose
his will through force over nature in
order to make life better for him all
right I think is really you know because
it encourages to sit encourages us to
see the world a bunch of stuff out there
that we can use any way that we like and
that seems to me to be right at the
heart of how we are able to treat the
world as we do and I'm not talking about
climate change just like mr. Peterson I
have deep suspicions about the climate
change narrative which is being forced
down my throat just for the very simple
reason that it's being forced down my
throat that makes me extremely
suspicious but there is no doubt that
the amount of plastic we're throwing
into the ground and into the enemies of
the water the toxification of freshwater
supplies is stripping the forests the d
the you know the lots of soil as a
consequence of deforestation the
chemical runoff the blah blah blah mean
is that there's a million things all of
which need urgent attention you know
species die awfully there are many many
things all of which need urgent
attention and for me the climate change
narrative is once again a distraction
from doing anything about all of these
things which actually there are ready
available solutions to instead we're too
busy squabbling about who's right over
climate change but anyway that to one
side that narrative and again for to mr.
Peterson thank you for internet Conrad
no it's not Conrad anyway thank you
again for introducing me to the idea of
the power of story to shape not only our
reality but the way that we function in
the world and but I but I do think
adhering to and internalizing
flawed stories is extremely dangerous
and and for me the judeo-christian
narrative of God man nature is is is
deeply deeply fought it encourages us to
exploit and destroy the world around us
and not to honor cherish worship it in
every action that in every action
interaction that we take with it there
is no way if we saw every being as
having a soul very much like our own
that we would treat our livestock the
way that we do for example you know we
love our pets and yet we go down and we
buy steaks anyway again it's not really
a thing I want to get into but but I
hope I've made my point
so yeah I'll just wrap up
okay so first of all it was Joseph
Campbell I was talking about not Joseph
Conrad he wrote parts of darkness of
course
Joseph Campbell was also very into
mythology on his whole life exploring
mythology from all over the world in
particular looking for similarities
cross-cultural cross temporal
similarities and then looking at
differences in order to isolate what was
cultural and what was you know deeply
embedded in the human psyche not
dissimilar to well in fact was informed
by Jung's work as is Jordan Peterson so
once again thanks to mr. Peterson for
not directing me there he didn't do it
personally but it was as a consequence
of listening to Jordan Peterson stuff
that I came across
Joseph Campbell as well so one of the
points that Campbell makes is that when
things are changing very rapidly it's
impossible for new mythologies to emerge
because it obviously takes time for them
to find expression and you know he was
he was writing primarily back in the 60s
70s but that saying is absolutely true
today even more so that things are
changing so quickly that is that it's
all but impossible for new myths new
stories to develop but I guess if there
is an overarching point to this video
then it would be a plea for people to
try and let will make room for the
possibility of new stories in their
minds and in their hearts because the
ones that we currently have our stories
of money are stories of judeo-christian
tradition our stories of power and so on
are all rooted in what Charles
Eisenstein refers to as the story of
separation where you know as I've
already talked about you know the
world's a bunch of stuff out there which
is which is for us to use and where
we're not in any way personally
connected with it in our stories don't
allow us to be you know we see
everything in physical terms that we
ourselves our awareness our
consciousness is nothing more than the
consequence of chemical reactions taking
place axons and
electrons and you know waves of energy
moving according to deterministic laws
and I mean I can't prove it's otherwise
but my own experience doesn't feel like
that nobody's experience feels like that
and so you know if it looks like a dark
and smells like a duck it's a duck or
whatever the phrase is is something like
that it escapes me exactly where it is
so yeah we really need to start coming
up with circulating reinforcing telling
ourselves new kinds of stories where the
underlying substrate is one of
connectedness and not of separation
because however much you deny the
reality of the fact that we are
connected to everything around us
everything around us if you know we're
part of it and it's part of us even if
you don't believe that it doesn't stop
it being true it doesn't stop the
consequences of our actions being
devastating ultimately to ourselves and
so you know if for nothing other than
self-interest we really need to start
developing some new stories anyway I'm
starting to repeat myself so thank you
very much for those of you that are
watching for watching and if you think
I'm saying interesting things then
please spread the word I guess
ultimately what I'm hoping is that this
gets back to Jordan Peters him himself
at Jordan Peters and himself and you
know that he thinks them worthy of
consideration and responds to them in
some way but you know that's unlikely
well who the am I 42 subscribers
right so anyway thank you very much for
watching I'll make something else soon
like